

Machine Learning Researcher · Data Scientist

 $\blacksquare$ rehanguha<br/>29@gmail.com | \$\mathbb{O}\$ (+91) 9874223189 | \$\mathbb{O}\$ India<br/> \$\mathbb{O}\$ rehanguha.github.io | \$\mathbb{in}\$ rehanguha | \$\mathbb{O}\$ rehanguha| \$\mathbb{E}\$G-Scholar

# Summary .

Let me start by giving a simple introduction about my work. I am a Senior Machine Learning Researcher presently employed by a product based company. I have worked in several ML projects mainly dealing with Optimization Problems, Explainable AI, Deep Learning, Imbalance Classification, et cetera...

I am also the author of a book "Machine Learning Cookbook with Python" published by BPB publications. I have been part of multiple publications through Journals and Open Publications, along with this I have few applied patents to my name.

Recently I was invited by Arizona State University to be a part of their team participating in CPS challenge 2020 funded by National Science Foundation(NSF), USA and sponsored by NASA. I have also conducted multiple seminars/webinars in this field of research for various universities and made contributions to Open Source Software as well.

Currently I am working on Open Source contribution for Google Tensorflow Addons and studying the behavior of multiple gradient based optimizers.

# Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

Pramati Technologies Chennai, India

#### **Senior Machine Learning Researcher**

Oct 2019 - Present

During this period I worked on Google TensorFlow SIG Addons for pushing a PR, and studying a behavior on Gradient based Optimizers.

Machine Learning Researcher

Oct 2018 – Sep 2019

I was responsible to integrate Fonduer in our pipeline. I also ran a project to Deniosing a Natural image using a random weights from a CNN structure.

#### Imaginea Technologies Inc.

Chennai, India

Senior Data Scientist Oct 2019 - Present

Managed the Data Science team of 2 including myself from Imaginea. Actively worked on their clinical dataset for increasing their coverage and accuracy for their existing scripts. For another project I was responsible for analyzing the CLV and building a Data Analytics dashboard.

Data Scientist Oct 2018 – Sep 2019

Handled Litigation Likelihood (LitLikelihood) module of the project – from data analysis to production deployment. Including Imbalance data classification I had a chance to work on another module where I have used LDA for Topic modeling.

Book Author India

BPB Aug 2019 - Nov 2020

A Cookbook that will help you implement Machine Learning algorithms and techniques by building real-world projects. Key Features:

- Learn how to handle an entire Machine Learning Pipeline supported with adequate mathematics.
- Create Predictive Models and choose the right model for various types of Datasets.
- Learn the art of tuning a model to improve accuracy as per Business requirements.
- Get familiar with concepts related to Data Analytics with Visualization, Data Science and Machine Learning.

Participant Part Time

ARIZONA STATEUNIVERSITY (ASU) & NATIONAL SCIENCEFOUNDATION (NSF)

May 2020 - Jun 2020

2020 CPS Challenge "SoilScope - Mars edition":

Mars 2020 inspired mission scenario for the 2020 NSF CPS Challenge will be a two-week virtual event, emulating an autonomous probe deployment sciencemission by a rover and drone duo, at the Jezero crater landing site.

Organizer:

Arizona State University, NASA

#### **Associate Software Engineer**

Chennai, India

ACCENTURE Jan 2017 - Sep 2018

I am working as a Machine Learning Developer at Accenture for multiple Research projects, and few of the research projects won awards and it has been considered as product by the company.

- Financial Service Development Project (Quartz Development) (Full Time, Managed team size of 2)
- Self Learning Credit Approval System (Part time, 3 months)
- Al Model Based Risk Management (Part time, 4 months)
- Ship and Air Cargo Routing (Part time, 2 months)
- Digital Content and Transaction Management using an Artificial Intelligence (AI) based Communication System ( Part time, 3 months)
- Routing System for Car Pool and Drop for the Employees (Part time, 3 months)

Bounty Hunter Part Time

HackerOne Jan 2017 - Present

Found and Resolved Bugs for:

Zomato

**Creator** India

PIXREAD Dec 2016 - Present

One of a kind OCR & 2D Codes (QR Code, Bar Code etc) search engine where the extracted text will be searched over a search engine. This will ease all the users to take a picture (which has text) from a device and search over different search engines.

Technical Associate Kolkata, India

Saltlake Institute of Engineering & Management Website Developer & SEO Professional

Aug 2015 - Feb 2015

#### **Publications**

# Digital Content and Transaction Management using an Artificial Intelligence (AI) based Communication System

Patent: US20200034842A1

MACHINE LEARNING, CREDIT RISK SCORING

Aug 2018

A system for predicting a non-fraud dispute using an artificial intelligence (AI) based communications system is disclosed. The system may comprise a data access interface to receive instructions historical transaction and disputes data from at least one data source associated with an account issuer. The data access interface may also receive incoming transaction data associated with a transaction from at least one data source associated with an account holder. The system may comprise a processor to predict a likelihood of a non-fraud dispute associated with the transaction by: examining the historical transaction and disputes data; retrieving non-fraud dispute attributes; parsing the incoming transaction data; applying predictive analytics to the incoming transaction data to yield a prediction value; determining that the prediction value meets a predetermined threshold; and generating a predictio for the likelihood of a non-fraud dispute associated with the transaction associated with the account holder to be outputted, via an output interface to a user device.

#### Prime Numbers - 1st One Lac

Dataset: %Link

Data, Numerical Jun 2016

Contains 1000 files with 100 prime numbers in each file.

#### Grid Searching - Novel way of Searching 2D Array

Journal: %Link

ALGORITHM, RESEARCH, SEARCHING

Description

Jan 2016

Biometric Ticketing System

Patent

ELECTRONICS, ARCHITECTURE, RAILWAYS

Mar 2014

Description

Data Security- Multi-Layer Folder Lock Hiding

Patent

ARCHITETURE, ALGORITHM Apr 2013

Description

Biometric Voting Machine Patent

ELECTRONICS, ARCHITECTURE, ELECTION Dec 2014

Description

Skills

Machine Learning: Imbalance Classification, Statistical Analysis

**Deep Learning:** CNN

## **Honors & Awards**

Runners-Up, In this challenge, we use a drone to search for and locate a soil probe. The drone picks up the probe and takes it to a drop-off location. Then, the drone must autonomously return to a rover and land in its trunk. This was accomplished using Rtabmap, a SLAM package used to estimate the position and velocity states of the rover with visual odometry and our own tailor-made Kalman Filter conflated with GPS based state estimation and the visual odometry based states.

\*\*National Science\*\*
Foundation (NSF) & Arizona State\*\*
\*\*University (ASU)\*\*

Aug 2018 Accenture Celebrates Excellence, Category - Innovation; Award type - Team Accenture

Mar 2018 **Asset Harvest Contest**, 1st Pace

May 2018 Accenture Celebrates Excellence, Category - Innovation; Award type - Individual

Nov 2017 **Accenture Celebrates Excellence**, Category - Client and Customer; Award type - Team

Accenture Institute of

Accenture

Accenture

 $\ \ \, \text{May 2015} \, \, \textbf{Student Performance Award}, \, \text{Received the award for excellence innovation and performace}. \\$ 

Engineering & Management,

# **Projects**

#### Bank of America (Quartz Development)

Python, Angular JS

Accenture

Kolkata

**Problem:** We had multiple tools of different technologies, and we require proficient resource to use the tools. Project was people driven.

**Action:** I made a platform for Environment Management team where all the automated scripts (for multiple technologies) & report generation tools will be placed & used from a single integrated platform with a simple UI.

**Result:** Saved a lot of manual effort, anybody with the access permission can use the tool can execute it using a simple UI with less or no knowledge of the technology, Project became Process driven.

#### **Self Learning Credit Approval System**

Python, ML, H2o.ai, Scikit-learn

Accenture

**Problem:** Rule based decision for approval of Credit which lead to loss of business.

**Action:** I was solely responsible for the development of the Machine Learning Algorithm.

**Result:** Accenture took this as a product and demonstrated to the client for identifying bad loans or missed opportunities, enable the bank to mitigate potential risk and opportunities

#### **AI Model Based Risk Management**

Azure, Python, H2o.ai

Accenture

Problem: High level of manual effort from Compliance officer for Risk Management to detect valid and type of alerts raised.

**Action:** I made an AI based Model using DeepLearning to detect the Alert and type of alert which is performed by Compliance officer.

**Result:** Dependency on the compliance officer will decrease, model will be capable to figure out new patterns in the generated alert.

#### **Ship and Air Cargo Routing**

Python, Machine Learning

Accenture

Problem: Ship and Air Cargo Routing for Logistics with high traffic and and more than expected loading time.

**Action:** Used key concepts of algorithm and process Design to optimize the whole system.

Result: Decreased the time for processing more than 20 seconds which improved the performance and saved huge money.

# Digital Content and Transaction Management using an Artificial Intelligence (AI) based Communication System

Python, Machine Learning, H2o.ai, Scikit-learn

Accenture

**Problem:** There were no existing intelligent model to predict Disputes of a transaction of a financial institute.

**Action:** I have designed a machine learning model which predicts both the dispute and the dispute category of a financial transaction given to the model using using a life dataset.

**Result:** Accuracy of the model with the live dataset came to be around 92%. The project is applied for patent by Accenture and will be sold as a product to the clients. This offering is expected to Reduce Annual Billing Disputes Volume by 30% i.e. 330K, lowering Ops Cost by USD 15.3 million and enhancing Customer Experience by guarding them from such dispute prone transactions.

### Routing System for Car Pool and Drop for the Employees

Python, Machine Learning, H2o.ai,

Scikit-learn
Accenture

**Problem:** There were no existing intelligent model to predict Disputes of a transaction of a financial institute.

**Action:** Created an software using Google Map and some grouping algorithm with considering total cars, total no of seat in each car, last drop should be a male for women security.

Result: Reduced the entire manual effort form sorting and assigning of the cabs

Python

PixRead

%Link

An Innovative Research Project which helps the users to extract the text from an Image using OCR and other image processing algorithms and search through different Popular Search Engines. Technologies used - OpenCV, Google Tesseract OCR, etc...

**AudioAnalytica** 

Python, Machine Learning,

SI ink

AudioAnalytica is a no-code platform and audio analytics dashboard. This is one of a kind All-in-One Audio analytics platform. There are no to less solutions who offer an audio analysis and analytics platform for general and not specific to one vertical. Dashboard for individuals looking to get insight from audio files and use those knowledge for their business with no knowledge of Audio Processing.

# **Education**

### Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur

DEEP LEARNING (AICTE APPROVED FDP COURSE)

Jul 2019 - Oct 2019

#### Institute of Engineering & Management, Kolkata

Kolkata, India

Bachelor of Computer Application (B.C.A.) in Computer Applications GPA: 8.5

2013 - 2016

# **Volunteering Experience**

Guest Lecturer

Nov 2018 – Present

I give Machine Learning & Data Science related Workshops to University students to bring them up the pace with the Moden World and Expose them to a new technology which they pursue in Future. Top Universities & Colleges visited so far

- KL University (Top 50 University in India)
- B.S. Abdur Rahman Crescent Institute of Science and Technology
- VELS University

## Other Information

• Father's Name: Ranjan Guha

• Nationality: Indian

• Allergries: None

• Philantrophy service:

• Hobbies:

#### Decalaration:

I hereby declare that all the information contained in this resume is in accordance with facts or truths to my knowledge. I take full responsibility for the correctness of the said information.